was it so well I guess starting
beginning Natalia I was saying
distinguishing the difference between
differently in the different assemblies
assemblies that are interested in who
were skilled in pretty words and
assemblies who were skilled in
interrogation in talking about
interrogation self interrogation kind of
them as opposed to inspirational poetry
exactly so being skilled he was being
well trained in being able to inquire
into your own understanding your own
views hmm and you know that I guess can
be quite a challenge together they have
to be prepared to articulate your views
and be open to criticism yeah
well not not to be taking it personal
yeah because it's not criticism yeah
yeah it's more of a just pointing out
the contradiction your understanding
like understanding like clarity so the
only way to benefit from it is to
basically learn how to not take it
personally because it's not personal
that is the thing yeah the fact that you
can always have greater understanding
means you can always improve but
whatever you have the starting point is
but not if you are afraid to even
question it because you can't help but
take it personally and that's why you
can also see where the person has a
valid argument or not is if somebody
points out like a certain lack in your
understanding that's the best thing they
can do for you because now you can
actually look at it and clarify from
contradiction development but if
somebody just starts attacking you like
a dominant person it means okay you
can't yeah if they just say I have no argument
yeah if they just say I have no argument
against what his view is I just don't
like the way he walks
did you see him walking that's not and
that's it as if that somehow relates to
invalidating the point you made that
obviously challenges so that's what we
like even you can find it in yourself
whether you are looking to blame for
false means okay so that means I'm
taking my peers personally yeah or if
you just get offended by somebody cuz
they presented a few like that should
already be a red flag for you yeah so so
we did a session last week where we were
kind of getting to inquire into our own
understanding anyway so and some of
these come up more recently where I've
kind of realized that perhaps Isis seem
to have a different understanding from
some of the things that you've been
saying so so maybe we can explore that
I'll see if there's any kind of
what problems there are there that we
can address and those about the p3
determine characteristics of the
determined the things about three places
and suitors you hear about these three
determined characteristics of the
determined so
to arrive so arising is manifest I say
go powder the powder pan yo t like
rising his manifest passing away loss or
decay is manifest and change while
standing and we have the tongue think
that certainly at the time upon yo T
change while enjoying his manifest and
salutes you understand okay so so how to
start so like so I've heard you say that
so arising is manifest is like the same
thing as saying something is increasing
in its presence or something is
decreasing in its presence either way
something is there in do you enduring
and at the point of that is because most
people would start with assumption then
you can observe the first point
yeah when thing begins yeah but you can
only find it as already being there
hence increasing this presence means it
implies having been there before you
even attended it directly so I think I
see the third characteristic in the same
way that's what you're saying the
go-go's girlfriend during and during
yeah that's something whether it's
whether arising is manifest to change
while standing it or passing away it's
manifest something is there to that
extent even use as a sink as the same
thing that we did yeah so I think my
third that's possibly the most important
it it is good that we did the third you
discern arising and cease yeah but I
seem to have a different understanding
of what the first two characteristics
are hmm so rather than so arising is
manifest so rather than it being that
there's a thing and that thing happens
to be arising or that thing happens to
be fading out
mmm-hmm because that that means that
you're sort of doesn't it there's this
thing and then there's the secondary
quality of it either arising or it fades
away but in order to get that you've
already presuppose this thing where is
these three characteristics or what
determines the thing so so what you said
a thing we refer to so how do you it can
attempt to yeah something like you're
getting something right well that's the
first thing isn't it it's on the level
of the characteristics of the
determinations and you can't attend to
them directly so these characteristics
yeah had to be understood yes only
experience is a whole level yeah you
can't know like I'm looking at that this
arises I'm looking at this ceases
yeah no it's experience the basic
experience as a whole that's where it's
already manifested yeah sorry the thing
three characteristics can't be attended
to but I think can be attended to sure
and I think is understood the as being a
thing by virtue of these three
characteristics these three
characteristics are what make or that
inversion which things are understood as
things that's what I think these rapid
you know the three characteristics
unless you think of them as things well
you be welded yeah you will be but it's
all I can say that basis and the base of
it experience how can then say that the
things are determined by three
consisting solely as in there are things
because they are determined by these
three characteristics why why the things
because they arise because they cease
because your position for what what for
whatever thing you can possibly imagine
these three characteristics are there
yeah sure that's the way I'd see it so
so these three characteristics are kind
of already given well as in it when
there's ever a thing
all three anything to the same extent
this this is seems to be well there's a
this is seems to be well there's a
difference yeah I think I think let's
let's bring it down on to practical
level as opposed to the thing is by the
virtue of this by the virtue of that how
are you feeling right now
overall okay so what's your presently
enduring mood so right now I guess I can
say I'm slightly nervous or slightly
kind of like I'm I know I miss you what
feelings were they involved down to
feeling nervous feeling like no sort of
let's say what is it Sam so it's overly
uncomfortable feeling yeah so would you
be able to attend to that would you be
able to designate it to me now if you
weren't there on its own no if you were
manifested on its own yeah if it's not
enduring for this two minutes that it
took you to describe it that's right so
it's there on it's only during yeah now
you can look we did that as well so
that's your basis that's like what
doesn't mean you can't look further than
that you could probably it doesn't it's
it sort of doesn't matter where you look
the point is wherever you look you will
find a thing the thickness of a thing
enduring so your mood will be there
given beforehand yeah
that's where you can stop doing what
you're doing think about it oh this is
how I feel yeah because that's how you
were feeling that's the feeling that's
manifested yeah but now you can choose
to focus on different things almost
slightly less general things so overall
you're a bit nervous but from a
different point of view say if I ask you
are you comfortable otherwise not just
like emotionally like sort of discomfort
because you're nervous do you have any
emotional discomfort on account of
you're presently enduring health for
example all that now so if you were to
focus on that that's positive that's a
good feel here so with that feeling be
able to be manifested to be described
and designated if you weren't there
now if it's not the reason there if it's
not enduring there on its own level so
that's that that's the thing like so
nobody denies that you can attend two
different parts but doesn't matter but
part your 10 doesn't matter how
particular you get what you are
attending to is because
you were giving an option to yeah you
couldn't attend it if you weren't there
enduring on its own so discerning that
pre attention sort of background that
you can know before you attend it yeah
that's I mean if you look at it directly
that's on the level of attention which
means now there is something else that's
pre-attentive so to speak as a basis for
your attention so when you say you have
three present enduring feelings how can
you possibly know that
sorry three presently 3d characteristics
enduring at the same time how can you
possibly know that
unless you are able to step outside of
the whole set up of already arisen thing
and see it or look all three are there
because for you it's either present
enduring mood that you just discovered
so to speak on the basis of order the
enduring being there manifested that if
you dwell on might start increasing your
nervousness okay rock compatibility and
so on so
so you're you seem you're saying that
this hoop are definitely the first
characteristic arising is arising is
manifest is to do with whether the thing
is increasing in its intensity
increasing in enterprise yeah yeah I
support you whether it's basically
ceramic at your going away so long to me
that's that's well no that is also that
it's changing yeah at the fact that if
it's increasing its intensity as we said
in the previous talk we recorded arising
how can you distinguish arising how can
you say my nervousness is increasing
unless is the same identity of the same
nervousness that you are aware of being
existing five minute or not but you can
recognize that something has arisen
there is something that's this thing
here which has arisen okay so so the
powder is not something which is how
could you recognize this thing that has
arisen unless the thing is already in
dirt that's it okay you can't be but the
house it also it so how do you then say
a thing is arising and ceasing and
enduring and I can see it all so you
know I don't arise them not said that's
the thing I'm not saying that so so okay
so so let's say this mood right now if
you're just proud of it before you go
further because I'm not sure if you
understood me
if thing is arising means it's already
persisting or changing if thing is
ceasing means it's already persisting or
changing yeah why because the rising and
ceasing is on one level persisting or
changing his of the another level
simultaneously present level which means
if you were to understand thoroughly the
third characteristic you imply
understanding of the other two there is
no arising without an enduring entity of
a thing that's arising towards you
there is no ceasing without an enduring
entity of a thing that ceasing away from
you see that's by the way in the neurons
is there so I've kind of come up with
this I find that I tend to say this
arising not as something which is coming
towards me I guess it's just a figure of
speech you know it's coming in she's
like not attempt it see that seems to
ten to me that like this your partner is not
to me that like this your partner is not
a kind of a partner is not a sort of
process or like something which is
taking time well no becomes a process if
you forget the fact that it's already
enduring and it is a pro to see that in
that way so basically something has
arisen it's it's there rather than not
being bad okay so this mood you want one
recognizes not only the mood but all
pada is not funny IOT the parlor is
recognized the actual so what's the
difference then between ceasing and
arising so so with this mood of
nervousness so if there has arisen if
arising is for you this thing is there
that's it doesn't involve the particular
lasting over five ten minutes then
ceasing will be for you think is not
there no a desiccant occasionally there
is some no no no so it's no I'm not this
so it's not that it's not that mood
which is ceasing because it can't have
arisen unbe ceasing at the same time so
what it was openness in this mood that's
there by now has arisen okay just
deliver previously simultaneously
slightly yeah simultaneously I recognize
though that that's that that involves
the quite pleasant jovial mood I was in
a few minutes ago when we were just
sitting out there dad's gone away so
he's dead cessation you referring to so
yeah so so faint so the fact that
something has emerged necessarily
implies that something else has faded
away so basically arising is one thing
so basically arising is one thing
ceasing is another thing that's what
you're saying yeah so how is that then
necessarily whereby if you don't
recollect though it's like it's like
points of view when something can learn
to attention something else goes out of
attention yes sure but unless you attend
how can you know what got out of
attention unless you choose to attend to
it again now you know peripherally that
this is this is this
attack this this has become this has now
become the to come to the fall has sort
of emerged where as something else's
stated am how would you know the a
jovial mood
unless you're recollecting it now on
account of a non jovial mood is right
here you choose to the code you choose
to look I see this is what was gone
that's that's more leaner than what I'm
describing to you that is basically
management effort type of thing after
this thing has affected me on the basis
of experience as a whole here I am
attending to relative like relatively
secondary aspects and that's the point
the memory of the previous thing is not
so the same footing as a cuddly dude
it's with implied within it so within
the arising of the first thing that's
how you're able to recollect other
things they weren't there before but
again but like so so so I'm saying I'm
like I just may be wrong I'm sure I'm
wrong that's the whole point of us like
but I seem to have this notion that
something in something having emerged
that necessarily means that other things
sort of aren't there and anything is
kind of you can't in my so basically my
left my my account of these three
characters it is a slight contribution
just what you sit if you see there are
things that are not there yeah I don't
mean that they're not there of like just
figured out not not the centrally own
experience I don't exactly right if your
expense anymore but they're there
peripherally okay and and the point that
said the point is the opposite so these
three characteristics of what the terms
of thing as a thing must involve others
other things so it's not it's not all so
back to the feeling said the idea of the
idea of like understanding tell me what
not here the you refer to this end as
should I even go to the prison the
enduring unpleasant unpleasant feeling
being present involves necessarily
pleasant feeling not being present okay
so why would then you cannot do one
that's not present why would that
qualify for cessation not cessation the
word isn't cessation is via which means
sort of loss or lack lack yeah so it's
just kind of so like a manifest it how
do I translate then the second
characteristic so if the if the first
one is like now as I come on his neck
yeah how is the first one then
translated well father generally
translation is arising or you might say
and arising emerge but but not is it not
it's not I don't I don't take it this is
what you're kind of being careful to
avoid this idea that arising means that
you can while or I know I know we're not
talking about something like that I'm
saying that but I'm trying to know
something like whatever to rebrand
whenever lacking the vo say oh it's not
cessation it's more like lack if it's a
lack means it's still there
just not as much yeah so what does that
mean for arising them it's it's present
as needs can be more present yeah means
that's increasing environment is
decreasing yeah but no but it's not but
you're you're attaching the bull powder
and the via is who the nervous feeling
whereas I'm not saying that I'm just
saying that whenever I record so I
recognize this nervous feeling
recognizing that nervous feeling
involves recognizing something has
emerged mm-hmm something has the lack
but not the same thing something else
other things have sort of given way for
that thing to be there well and this
seems to me like that you can't you
can't understand a thing without
reference so one of the things it's
inconceivable of thinking of something
there's completely independent of other
things so if arising is manifested as
one of the characteristics yeah why
doesn't say that the rising is the term
determined by the other characteristics
that then determine things is things it
just says arising is this
so not that that says that this thing is
recognized as arrival no that's what you
just said now you said that the rising
is known by basically other things that
have ceased but this list characteristic
in itself basically arising is
manifested yeah but your argument now
for secession let me finish your
argument for sensation then is that
cessation determines arising as arising
and you can only arrive at that view by
comparing the two which is exactly how I
see what you're saying now by saying
that see by something arising means
other things are ceasing you are not to
the level of experience as a whole which
is always that unified the alertness the
German world which I'm sure you're
familiar with no you step down from
which you can look okay this thing is
arising but now when I attend to them
the only way you can attend to arising
an attempt to ceasing like at the same
time so to speak from one to the other
is because you are not at the level of
experience as a whole what I'm talking
about is on the level of experience in
the whole you're going to find only two
things either increasing his presence or
decreasing in his presence
simultaneously means it's in urine but
you're impure applying the arising is is
pressurizing his manifest presence on
that fundamental level you'll either one
audios and you're applying those arising
is manifesting in manifest to the same
thing what no they're different
experiences no but you're saying so this
Iraq so Iraq the thing is rather arising
all the thing is passing away its how
many don't see happen it's less of them
other thing because there seems to be a
little for you in order to imply
something you are heavily attending and
compare them okay experience as a whole
the most general terms yeah it's either
increasing it it's manifested that's
where you can talk about it yeah but
what I'm referring to is a that
manifestation can be arising or it can
be lacking whichever you want to
translate it so I there is no comparison
between the two I want to say that it's
like that arising autumn's
cessation is actually on the level of
the thing chain
while it's indoors yeah yeah yeah so
that's the third characteristic not the
first or second the first and second
characteristic is simply the thing has
arisen something that arising the
phenomenon of having arisen or arising
is discerned so the phenomenon of lack
or loss or gone away that's also
discerned so basically not the same
thing that has arisen and he's just that
they're not those phenomena her better
yeah I see I know what you're saying but
the point is there how can you then not
say it's not temporal
because it's not well I don't see that
simple but that's just like us because
oh look
now it's arising no you see the you
reckon whenever you recognize something
you recognize the mood ring you get all
this this has arisen when could not
blend emphasis and I can't get Lux
inconceivable it's just some time ago I
don't know I recognize its name to be
exams I do you mean by arising it's so
you say yourself the mood I am in yeah
came to be whatever you want to call it
so why would you then now or how rather
can you be comparing the idea of this
other move that's not this more than a
mean is relevant to this mood and I mean
by not being dead moon but I'm still in
the fundamental level of the mood and
I'm not comparing the mood with my
attention because can't you and can't
you only understand a thing in terms of
other things so I know that's what he
always boils down to the convergence
points of feeling so for instance you
don't need to know are the feelings in
order to know that it's unpleasant it's
felt unpleasantly it requires zero to your
unpleasantly it requires zero to your
perceptual concern comparisons and
conceptions it's felt like this or it's
felt like this or it's felt like neither
that is there is no below that threshold
and that's my whole point when it comes
to the thing that has manifested as it
mood as a whole you can't leave the
feeling out but once you start comparing
what has ceased what has not ceased like
it can all make sense but it's going to
be on the level of you
perceiving it and comparing it which
means it's not in the fundamental level
of enduring experience as a basis of all
of the acts you make yeah all of all of
what I'm saying is that's all given that
this there's this third characteristic
of whatever whatever this poo powder
whatever this via is is there is this
thing enduring which makes always
possible in the first place well no see
again that's that's basic emotions like
an explanation oh there is this there is
this because in the news which is why
this is all possible how can you think
of that which makes this possible unless
that's being experienced right now which
means there is something else that makes
it possible but how can you think that
unless you assume the external point of
view to yourself that then explains how
all this is possible for me that's the
whole point where I'm saying is a rising
ceasing enduring is on the level of
phenomenology if you start explaining it
you form from it you fall from the basis
of mindfulness that's the entire point
and you will do that as soon as you
start comparing the things like that
means you are not anymore on the
fundamental threshold where thing is but
if you say this this thing is and these
are the things our columns means that's
already on implication out of a second
experience now what I'm trying to say is
the the fact that something has arisen
is only possible because it's already
enjoying this yeah that's what I'm you
saying all the time changing while
standing decreasing is already changing
while standing so so so we're trying to
differentiate now is between what's the
difference for you then between the
rising and CC yeah that's it over our
enduring yeah between the rising and
ceasing what's a rather what is the relevant
what's a rather what is the relevant
difference don't give me like over you
can give me of course but I'll disagree
with it
comparison because that makes no
different that understanding makes no
difference to you freedom from suffering
yeah I guess if you were to truly
understand the characteristics of
determined and so on you would be unable
to to exercise any attitude of craving
or Rupa done as well but you knowing
that this particular thing that I chose
to attend this jovial mood is not here
has ceased on account of another mood
it's present that makes no difference
to the fact that you were affected by
the currently present mood yeah it's
determine its management its secondary
to it so these are the fundamental
characteristics if you understand them
you'll be unable to exercise any any
attitude of assumption or padana towards
experience the whole which means you
will be free from suffering
so how's your nervousness now or the
uncomfortable feeling when I can't to
the situation than it was before
but he said the same thing I'm saying
but there is a difference now isn't it
yeah when we started this there was a
greater prospect of it which wasn't
there but it was kind of going that way
now when you look back 15 minutes ago
you could say well the experience is
still there of their nervousness but now
it's basically going a different
direction and that's what you are
finding the reason why this is important
to find or certainly distinguishes there
is no end of thing arising as if there
is no subject that this is arising -
yeah and equally if you start asserting
the characteristic of ceasing that will
make us toward me or away from me the
more you familiar with it
the less able you will be to maintain
the notion of me yeah because you
realize oh this just goes and then next
thing I know there is no it has arrived
at me resisted and now it's going away
from you no only seeds increasing and
then always seedling or no the creases
are it is a posture and only me then
assumes increasing for me increasing
away from me but if you keep looking at
the clock as increasing and decreasing
as more fundamental than your notion of
self your notion of self will fade
because you're only maintaining it to
the gratuitous assumption as the kind of
receiver or the originator of depending
on the direction when you realize
directions don't need any subject
arising is manifestly
ceasing is manifest either way you
discern thing indoors on its own without
requiring your ownership your control
your sense of self yeah now that's
something I hadn't seen before so yes
this does and that's why I could
directly spring from some why it's
useful important or worthwhile you start
to discern well that's always a little
tedious direction criteria you should
use whatever comes to anything basically
from the suitors yeah if I'm
understanding this rightly I should be
basically free from suffering all the
way to be so will never ever gave things
unless they're obvious kind of just
talking about culture or whatever else
never gave things that pertain to the
Dharma we'll be explanations they were just
we'll be explanations they were just
sort of so like explain things to her
this is why this occurs if he said that
means it needs to be understood and if
it's understood right that means you'll
be free from suffering so if you think
you're understanding that's fine you
can't help that but then you have to
take a step further and okay so I
understood this such-and-such degree am
i then directly uprooting at Avada as a
result of this do I feel less able to
suffer as a result of this how does this
pertain to me being affected by the
presently enduring feeling whatever that
feeling is and if you don't quite see
how means you haven't understood it
enough and that's why if you were to
understand the rising your understanding
enduring if you were to understand
ceasing your understanding enduring if
you were to understand both your
understanding enduring either way your
understanding the full picture that
doesn't require an agent of meat I am my
sense of self to maintain this ownership
and control of things that's where the
Buddha said some monks become skilled in
discerning arising someone's become
skilled in searcy singsong this become
become skilled in selling very enduring
by the way any of those things can serve
as understanding the fundamental
principle they will uproot your sense of
self so that's what I mean like things
and things and this is not here this is
not okay that's all fine but you want to
go as far as you can in terms of the
fundamental level in terms of the
general experience as a whole so the
most fundamental thing is how I feel
that's what things converge okay so
instead of okay that's just say what you
said there was like okay that's that's
really helpful and but let's still
clarify why what I was saying before is
not no let's instead get you to clarify
now how you understood what I said don't
tell me how I you were wrong before then
we might understand why you were wrong
before so what's your present enduring
mood rooted in the feeling and chose the
first thing so saying just like
a slight feeling of uncomfortable
comfortable but is it fading away or is
it there yeah it's it's yeah it's going
kind of a wait going kind of away and so
right so recognizing the mood can either
be going away or coming densifying
coming there is no end after which you
will see on now it's gone and it is no
it's not a point x2 point why it's
simply a direction what are you going to
see like in this particular instance now
you'll be seeing it's going away and
then we'll talk about other things in
the day and then you're it's gone as in
now something else is present the more
you recognize the more you recognize
that characteristic is that direction
data simple direction the less you're
going to be a Sumerian points here and a
point there yeah and what's the problem
with any form of assuming the end point
or B in itself here and what's the
characteristic of a self view why is
itself your problem by self you why is
that divider problem what's the main
characteristic about Nevada well it's
sort of an assumption of a sort of
control over something which you have
known because you stuff up in the hands
of it no ok software is a symptom that
there is something should there but what
would be the characteristic of the
problem a lot of other as in what is it
what characteristic of other other makes
it a problem which then ties in with
assuming the endpoint or assuming the
receiving point they all have one thing
in common
that's a problem which is why they're
all problem that thing is basically
assuming an external point of view to
your own ability and the problem and you
can ask why gsella from it's because it
cooks a contradiction in terms because
you can't have something outside you
assuming an endpoint of this experience
of mind is a serious illness the point
of view that's independent of this
experience of mind that's only the first
contradiction if you can then just
witness the ending point after which
something out here comes here so you are
there not there but how can you talk
about it unless you talk about in the
basis of your experience yeah that's why
antibodies a problem no other reason
because it maintains a gratuitous view
that cannot be experienced as such
I just wanna so say again so recognizing
becoming more and more sensitive to
being able to discern clearer and
clearer this direction of either coming
up or intensifying or going away it's
not concerning the nature that they're
exactly here and that's why I see if you
study selling the nature you are
automatically less involved with the
content and event which is increased if
you don't know that you would be chasing
and focusing and concentrating on the
moment-to-moment content hoping you
catch a breaking point after which thing
isn't another I would apply those ten
directions suddenly stop exactly then
would again so the attitude of
meditation technique for example of
catching every moment not lapsing every
movement order this root 2 then in
assumption of its still upon of unit to
your experience as a whole yeah
hence which is actually just a conceived
and the only reason the person will be
maintaining that point of view is
because they don't clarify they don't
question it they don't discern it this
might be point massage because I'm just
kind of yeah them want a flock data loss
they say yeah so now okay no you can do
it yourself
yeah from the point of view that you
understood now as in the relevance of
what I was saying yeah and see how that
stacks against where you are where you
were yeah what come you do it now yeah so but
yeah what come you do it now yeah so but
you do yeah so um okay so I can see now
the importance of
like I said because I becoming familiar
with this that general direction of
either increasing in presence let's call
it a rising hmm I'm decreasing presence
let's call it fading out and the thing
is I've been careful with those words
before because putting it in those terms
what makes it sound temporal yeah so so
maybe that was sort of I was undercover
throwing the baby out with the bathwater
I was getting rid of something useful to
show that was scared of sure yeah and
but I still have this sense that the
party's manifesto buyer is manifest but
that they they are okay I still have
this sense that what we're talking about
here as a thing arising becoming
stronger becoming bigger becoming more
intense or something fading out I still
have a sense that that's the third
characteristic of only after time the
change yeah well that's because they did
the basis of experience of arising say
that's the basis within CC you can't
focus on more particular things they
would be ceasing or arising but the
point is but that you're looking at the
fundamental so even if you're saying see
these things are Epson now they're only
the basis of presently increasing
experience as a whole of such-and-such
mood but it's just looking at the parlor
if if yeah the time the reason why I
would state say no to what you're about
to say is because it would be on the
level of explanation and if it's an
explanation it's on open angle because
if you were to understand it on the
level you're talking about makes no
difference to the wrong view of
after rather than anything else if you
understand the long talk about makes the
whole difference but all I'm trying to
argue for still applicable even to the
other point and I've said probably to
some extent is but it isn't because then
it's not a dumb but isn't isn't please
let me just try to say God maybe it's
completely wrong I just feel any taxes I
get it's out there that you've got this
third characteristic we should change so
harder being manifest and vibing being
manifest that's something different from
the thing changing so so arising it
manifest failing homes manifest change
while stylings Munford the thing is
changing while it indoors which means
that those first two I'm not about
changing it's just about up just arisen
as arisen
that's how can you find arising without
already that being a form of changing
arising but you just described with you
trying to say each one is you say it's
arising well you know it's your
description that ends up making it
basically like a starting point
it has arisen is what I'm trying to get
on I'm trying to I guess of so come down
it has arisen
yeah means it was before means the same
thing is still there enduring and
changing and you can say it has a reason
yeah unless if you were right you would
then be able to measure the point after
which thing has a white copy then say
that arising is not changing what
standard there it's already arisen I
can't like you can't it's not a temporal
thing is just can you make a statement
how can you make it
that it's already arisen how can you not
spend that time designating it without
things still remaining the same if you
were correct you would be unable to
speak better your designation would take
too long and the thing would cease by
the time you designate in which your
sentence because yeah if thing has a
reason no and it's not your doing as an
identity of a thing I'm not saying it
isn't it like the third characteristic
is still there but what it says is
Aeneas Lee arising is also it's just a
lot arising is something different
that's why there's three so three
different things yeah but they're many
different ways you can understand how
they're different yeah
so if a rising is existing or changing
what's the difference then well between
the rising and ceasing if they're both
persisting were changing what's the
difference between them simply the
phenomenon of having arisen is discerned
what is then the phenomenon of ceasing
the phenomenon of ah not them anymore
but how can talk about it if it's not
there anymore well and so that's the
thing that's why I've sort of been
saying it's more a kind of fading out
okay so which means in the rising is
which now brings it in to fading out
yeah tell me that in a minute but it's
just you be sticking with your
explanation of arising then he
contradicts your own explanation of
ceasing as he just did
because you see Singh is fading out
arising is fading in yeah yeah I've just
basically explained the same thing that
I was trying to review before yeah it's
been quite actually yeah they are that's
the only distinction you can make the
fading position why would I have this
notion that it's not the same thing so
yeah don't mean they kept saying you
keep comparing yeah yeah I guess this
feeling in which case in which case yeah
it has
today it's the same thing there which
case the fading house and the fading in
can't be seeing that same thing as now
so those are the if you were to like not
abandoned diamond origin by that I mean
stop you don't give into assuming the
external point of you to experience the
only distinction you can make between
that which is manifest is whether it's
increasing or decreasing
either way it's being enduring while
it's manifested they say yeah I bit the
mate and the main thing is not that this
isn't just a kind of it's a other than a
happy well how about this the important
thing I want to say this is not just
intellectual games knowing here it's
like I'm now come away with this idea
that it's important to keep discerning
just that basic quality of Iraq of
increasing that's what we get that's why
that basic quality that's important to
this Ernest is basically on the middle
way here in the middle is it's you can
overdo it in which case you overshoot it
which case it won't be that in dealing
with talking about or you can sort of
understood it in which case again you
won't be that enduring we're talking
about here and already why it isn't an
abstraction because if you start seeing
things in there arising as in the the
nature of increasing doesn't matter what
how because of which because that it's
present basically remaining the same
while increasing or remaining the same
while decreasing if you forced you to
stay on the level of the nature of
experience which means it will basically
start fading away
removing the necessary basis for the
maintenance of our tamada
and the necessary basis is the very act
of assumption of an external point of
view you go after your experience you
can't even bother
without engaging in our to bother it is
this such common yeah
by rising in 61 the body is manifest to
extend this to the extent necessary
final knowledge so that's their so -
Jules yeah
and that's if you have the rising CC
change well enduring then full change
while persisting that change while
persisting he's like the general aspect
yeah and the change while position is
the change this is the change but it's
increased or decreased air rises what
the system yeah there's rising the
seasoning is just didn't work particular
smaller Hospital yes general think the
rising so yeah change so really so
that's the thing so understanding this
mindfulness new mindfulness right Lee
I've always been over attending the
enduring and not giving enough attention
to the change in thinking that's not so
sure important if where it where is
actually recognizing those changes as a
as to inherent directions without
endpoints and another reason why those
recognizing those directions does this
the piece is about yeah and another
reason why they are relevant is because
it also corresponds to your craving it's
the same principle
pleasure is increasing you want pain to
decrease you want it you want the
direction of it going away you have want
the direction of increasing so if what
you want to increase is actually not
increasing as yourself a lesson isn't
that craving also sort of obsessing over
the endpoint well exactly you can't have
craving without assuming an external
point even I can't have craving without
having after vada
so you recognize their general direction
is that which has to be one of the other
means you stop assuming the endpoint
yeah so if you know just that you will
be free from an Tabata if you discern
these three characteristics on the level
of your mindfulness you'll be free from
sexuality and you'll be free from your
will and then you'll be free from
conceit as well and that's what we said there
as well and that's what we said there
before with a busted-up when he
clarified the petite Savannah before he
became another hand he understood the
principle of basically simultaneous
presence as in that is that which
endures on account of which there is
increasing or decreasing
he remained contemplating as the suitor
translates arising with the five
aggregates as in either way enduring is
there and he remained fully mindful of
it correctly so no no no amount of
arising of any of the Farragut's or
cesium America families has induced any
more of the wrong assumption of external
point of view in regard to his own
experience and that's why he was freed
from each we were saying in another two
roots of Adama to tin Yan and the
knowledge of the insurance of things is
it